In the last lecture, you learned how to call set state correctly
Ve son ders, souk devlet nasl ayarlandn rendim.
if your new state depends on your old state and there is a danger of editing this old state at the same
Yeni devletiniz eski durumunuza balysa ve bu eski devletin baka herhangi bir yerde
point of time anywhere else in the application because set state actually runs asynchronously.
ayn anda dzenleme tehlikesi varsa, nk bu devlet aslnda zaman uyumsuz olarak alr.
Now as we have a good way for setting the state in such cases, we also have a better way of handling
imdi, bu gibi durumlarda sahneyi ayarlamak iin iyi bir yol olduumuzdan, en azndan baz kullanm durumlarnda pervanelerin
props at least in some use cases this might be better,
daha iyi bir ekilde ele alnmas daha iyi olabilir.
mostly if you write components which might be used by other developers during their development process.
ounlukla, gelitiricilerimiz tarafndan geliim sreci boyunca kullanlabilecek bileenleri yazarsanz, sahne
You can restrict the types and values you receive for your props, like for person.js,
tasarmclar iin aldnz tr ve deerleri kii iin olduu gibi kstlayabilirsiniz.
there we receive four important props,
J. S. orada drt nemli sahne alyoruz.
click, name, age and changed.
Ad yan tklayn ve deitirildi.
Now since it's our application and we test it regularly, we have no danger of passing the wrong values probably
Uygulamamzdan beri dzenli olarak test edilmitik, muhtemelen yanl deerleri geme tehlikesiyle kar karyayz, ancak yan
but we can still enforce certain values to really ensure that age always is a string or a number and
daima bir dize veya say olduundan emin olmak iin belirli deerleri zorlayabiliriz ve ad her zaman
the name always is a string or a number, like in our case,
bizim gibi bir dize veya saydr. vaka.
app.js age is a number.
Aslnda ya bir say gibi.
Now if we were to pass a string, our app would still work correctly but maybe we do some calculations
imdi, bir dizgeyi iletirsek uygulamanz yine de dzgn alacaktr, ancak belki de bununla baz
with that and therefore we definitely need a number.
hesaplamalar yapyor ve bu nedenle kesinlikle bir numaraya ihtiyacmz var.
Then we want to make sure that a warning or an error is thrown during development
Sonra gelime srasnda bir uyar veya bir hata Frode olduundan emin olmak istiyoruz.
if a developer uses our component incorrectly. Put in other words, we want to check the types of the incoming
Eer bir gelitirici bileenimizi yanl kullanyorsa, gelen zelliklerin doru ekilde kullanldndan emin
properties to make sure that they are getting used correctly.
olmak iin trlerini kontrol etmek istiyoruz.
And for that there is an extra library or extra package you can add to your react app
Ve bunun iin tepki verecek ekstra bir ktphane veya ekstra paket var.
so let's do that. I'll do this with the built-in terminal and there I'll run npm install --save to save
Bu yzden btn Dudas' dahili terminal ile yapalm ve pakete bitiik dosyadaki girdiyi kaydetmek iin
the entry in the package.json file and then it's simply called prop types.
kurulum izgi izgi kaydn altrn ve sonra sadece Propp trleri denir.
This is by the react team just outsourced into its own package and gives us access to some utility
Bu, yeniden hareket ekibi tarafndan sadece kendi paketine dntrlm ve mlkmzn trn kontrol etmek
features to check the type of our property.
iin bize yardmc program zelliklerine erimemizi salyor.
So here in the person.js file,
Yani burada kii JS yanltr.
we can use it by
Kullanabiliriz.
first of all importing prop types from that package.
ncelikle bu paketten Propp trlerini ie aktarn.
So import prop types.
Yani Propp trlerini ie aktarn.
That's the default export of this package from prop types, like this.
Bu paketin Propp trlerinden varsaylan olarak da aktarlm olmasdr.
Now how do we use prop types then? You simply use it by going below your class definition then taking
imdi pervane tiplerini nasl kullanacaz, o zaman snf tanmnzn altna giderek snfnz alarak
your class,
bunu kullanabilirsiniz.
so person that is the name of this class in the end and there, you now simply add the prop's type
Dolaysyla, bu snfn ad ve sonu olan kii, imdi sadece uygun trn
property,
mlkn eklemelisiniz.
you're basically editing this class after it was defined. Prop types is a javascript object and there you
Temelde bu snfta dzenleme yapyorsunuz, Propp tiplerini bulmak iin bir jousted nesne buluyordunuz ve
can now have key value pairs where your keys or properties are the names of the props,
imdi anahtarlarnz veya zellikleriniz sahann adlar olan anahtar deer iftlerine sahip olabilirsiniz.
so click name and so on and the values are the conditions, the rules. So here, you could say we have a click
Yani adn tklatmak vb. Ve deerler kurallara gre koullar bu nedenle bir
property, conditions about to follow,
tklama mlkiyet artlar olduunu syleyebiliriz.
we have a name property, an age property and a change property.
Bir isim mlkiyet ya mlkmz ve bir deiim mlkmz var.
Now all the conditions are missing and after this lecture, you'll find an article where I list all available
imdi tm koullar eksik ve bu dersin ardndan mevcut durumu listelediim makaleyi
conditions
bulacaksnz.
you may add and you may use for defining your rulesets. Now for example you could say that click should
imdi kullanabilirsiniz, rnein, proc trlerine eriebilmeniz iin klick'in bir ilev olmas gerektiini syleyebilirsiniz.
be a function, so you can access prop types,
Ekleyebilir ve kural setlerinizi tanmlamak iin
that's this object you're importing from the prop types library and that exposes a couple of different rules
Veri, tr kitaplndan ie aktarldnz nesneyi yapar ve uygulayabileceiniz birka farkl kural veya
or types you can enforce.
tr ortaya koyar.
For example func and with that you are saying the value I get passed into my click property has
rnein, func ve benim klick mlkiyetime geirilen deerin elbette ok mantkl bir ilevi olmas
to be a function which of course makes a lot of sense because we're trying to execute it as a function.
gerektii syleniyor yars, bunu ad iin bir ilev olarak
For name,
yrtmeye alyoruz nk.
we might say prop type should be a string and for age, prop types might be a number.
Diyelim ki Propp trleri H iin bir dizge olmal, pervane trleri bir numara olabilir.
And by the way, there are even more advanced types you could even to define the exact shape of an object
arada aldnz bir Optik'in tam eklini bulmak iin bile daha gelimi trler bulabilirsiniz.
you're receiving,
Ve bu
so which properties it should have and which types the properties of that object should have.
Bu nedenle hangi zelliklere sahip olmal ve o nesnenin zelliklerinin hangi trleri olmaldr.
You can get really detailed
Gerekten ayrntl bilgi alabilirsiniz.
and again I strongly recommend having a look at the article after his lecture to learn about all the
Ve yine tm olaslklar renmek iin konferansndan sonra makaleye gz atmanz iddetle
possibilities
tavsiye ederim.
as there are a lot. So here, changed
ok ey olduunu sordu bylece deimisin.
maaybe should also be a function and that is a very basic prop type setup.
Belki de bir ilev olmalsn ve bu ok basit bir Propp tr kurulumdur.
Now if we go back to the application and reload, go to the console to see any potential error messages,
herhangi bir olas hata mesajn grmek iin konsola gidin, her eyin ie yaradn greceksiniz.
you'll see everything works.
imdi, uygulamaya geri dnp
Now if we try to pass a wrong property though for example by going to the app.js file and setting the
rnein, yakalama dosyasna giderek ve Max yan bir dizge olarak
age of Max to 28 as a string, now you see if I click toggle persons, we get an error here,
28 olarak ayarlayarak yanl bir mlk gemeye alrsak, imdi gei yapanlar tklarsam burada hata olur.
failed prop type, invalid prop age of type string,
Baarsz komut tr, geersiz Propp yandaki tr dizesi.
expect that number.
Bu numaray bekleyin.
This is exactly what we get there
Tam olarak oraya geldik.
and why is this helpful to us,
Ve neden bu bize yardmc oluyor.
we ensure that we're not receiving wrong props.
Yanl sahne almamza izin veriyoruz.
And again this is mostly useful if you're working in team, if we are building components which get used by other persons,
Ve yine de, bu, ounlukla, eer kii dizileri tarafndan kullanlm ekip oluturma bileenleri iinde
by other people and where it's crucial that you get the right props, because maybe sometimes you have props
alyorsanz ve doru sahneyi almanzn kritik olduu yerlerde yararldr, nk belki bazen bir dize olup olmadn
where it doesn't really matter if it's a string or a number because you're just printing it to the screen
gerekten de nemli olmayan bir sahne dzenei vardr. Bir say, nk onu herzaman ekranda
anyways,
yazdryorsunuz demektir.
In other cases, it might matter.
Ortalama durumlarda nemli olabilir.
So you don't have to use prop types in every component you define,
Yani tanmladnz her bileende pervane tipleri kullanmak zorunda deilsiniz.
again one reason that speaks against it is that it doesn't work in functional components which you
Buna kar konuan bir sebep de, mmkn olmad kadar sk kullanmanz gereken
should use as often as possible though.
ie yaramayan ve ilevsel bileenler olmamasdr.
But in some root level components, you might want to control which property enters it and which property
Ancak baz rube seviyesi bileenlerinde, hangi mlkn kendi menfaatleri ve mlknzn hangi zelliklerden getiini kontrol
you pass on
etmek isteyebilirsiniz.
and again especially important if you work with or for other people.
Ve dier insanlarla birlikte alrsanz ya da bakalar iin zellikle nemlidir.